<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the workbook                        -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--    Math 2500: Linear Algebra                             -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2014  Theron J. Hitchman                   -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->


<chapter xml:id="chapter-basic-objects" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <title>Vectors, the Dot Product, and Matrices</title>

  <introduction>
    <p>
      This first chapter introduces the basic objects of linear algebra.
      You will meet vectors, the dot product, matrices, and the computational
      system SageMath.
    </p>
    <p>
      Vectors are a generalization of the concept of number. Where real numbers
      can help us model the geometry of points on a line, vectors will allow us to
      model the geometry of a plane, or (three-dimensional) space, or even "spaces"
      with higher dimensions. We begin by learning about the algebra of vectors,
      and making connections to the geometry.
    </p>
    <p>
      The dot product is a funny kind of multiplication. It plays an important
      role in mathematics because it captures all of the basics of measurement.
      We shall learn how to use the dot product to measure lengths and angles. By
      its definition, the dot product is connected with the concept of a linear
      equation, so it will make frequent appearances in our work.
    </p>
    <p>
      Matrices are another way to generalize the concept of number. (In fact, they
      generalize the concept of vector.) We start here by learning about the
      algebra of matrices. The whole rest of this course will focus on matrices,
      their uses, and their properties.
    </p>
    <p>
      A running theme for this course is the use of the SageMath mathematical software
      system. In order to get started, the fourth section of this course is
      dedicated to getting started with SageMath using the SageMathCloud (SMC). You will
      make an account and run through an introductory workshop with SMC.
      Also, throughout this workbook you will find little embedded pieces of SageMath
      code. These are implemented using the SageMath SingleCell server. Most of these
      SageMath cells are mutable. You can change the content in them and re-evaluate
      your new SageMath code. I encourage you to play with these---it is a good way to
      learn the basics of SageMath.
    </p>
    <p>
      The fifth and final section of the chapter is a short assignment designed to
      consolidate learning. You will get a chance to practice your skills and to
      think more deeply about the concepts you have learned.
    </p>
  </introduction>


  <xi:include href="vectors.xml" />
  <xi:include href="bo-sage.xml" />
  <xi:include href="dot-product.xml" />
  <xi:include href="matrices.xml" />
  <xi:include href="bo-gf.xml" />


</chapter>
