<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the workbook                        -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--    Math 2500: Linear Algebra                             -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2014  Theron J. Hitchman                   -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<section xml:id="start-sage">
  <title>Getting Started with SageMath</title>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Assignment</title>

    <p>It it is time to get comfortable with the basics of using Sage. Begin by
      setting up an account with SageMathCloud.</p>

      <ul>
        <li><p>Be sure that you have login access to computers in student labs across
          campus. Before class, drop by a campus lab and make sure your credentials
          work properly and you can sign in to a machine. For our lab session
          we will use one of the labs on the first floor of Wright Hall, so one
          of those would make a good choice.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            Make an account SageMathCloud with your UNI Gmail account and sign in.
            This may be easier if you follow the invitation email you will receive
            from your instructor. If you have trouble with this step, email your
            instructor for help before 5pm the day before this is due.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            Find the project labelled Linear Algebra Fall 2016, and in it the
            folder marked "introductory workshop." Read through the <c>.sagews</c>
            file in this folder. Try out the exercises in it. Adjust some commands,
            play, and get familiar. If you have questions, make a list to bring to
            our lab meeting.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
      <title>Learning Objectives</title>

      <p>At the end of this assignment, a student should have an account at
        SageMathCloud and should be able to log into the service without trouble.
        The student will also have a first project with some files. The student
        will have at least tried some basic SageMath commands.
      </p>
      <p>
        The student should also be familiar with basic course policies as
        outlined on the syllabus, and will have generated a list of questions
        to ask the instructor about those points which are unclear.
      </p>
    </subsection>

</section>
