<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the workbook                        -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--    Math 2500: Linear Algebra                             -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2014  Theron J. Hitchman                   -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<section xml:id="section-least-squares">
  <title>Properties of the Determinant</title>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Assignment</title>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Read section chapter 5 section 1 of Strang.
      </li>
      <li>
        Read the following and complete the exercises below.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </subsection>
  <subsection>
    <title>Learning Goals</title>
    <p>At some point, a student should be able to compute the determinant of a
      square matrix using the properties outlined here.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection>
    <title>Discussion: The Determinant</title>
    <p>
      Generally, the most interesting matrices to look at are the square ones.
      For square matrices, there is an important number called the
      <term>determinant</term> which helps us determine if the matrix is
      invertible or not.
    </p>
    <p>
      Strang lists 10 important properties of determinants in this section,
      and verifies them for <m>2\times 2</m> matrices. The verifications for
      general matrices aren't any harder, but they sure are <emph>longer</emph>,
      so I am glad he skipped them. Anyway, these properties are enough to get
      by when it is time to compute. In fact, clever use of these properties
      can save you a lot of time.
    </p>
    <ol>
      <li>The determinant of the identity matrix is always one: <m>\det(I)=1</m>.</li>
      <li>If we exchange two rows of a matrix, the determinant changes sign.</li>
      <li></li>
      <li></li>
      <li></li>
      <li></li>
      <li></li>
      <li></li>
      <li></li>
      <li></li>
    </ol>

    <subsubsection>
      <title>Interpretation</title>
      <p>
        Suppose that an <m>n\times n</m> matrix <m>A</m> is represented as a
        collection of its column vectors:
        <me>
        A = \begin{pmatrix}
        | &amp; | &amp;  &amp; | \\
        v_1 &amp; v_2 &amp; \dots &amp; v_n \\
        | &amp; | &amp;  &amp; |
        \end{pmatrix} .
        </me>
        Then the geometric significance of the determinant is this: The number
        <m>\det(A)</m> represents the <emph>signed</emph> <m>n</m>-dimensional
        volume of the <m>n</m>-dimensional box in <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> with sides
        <m>v_1, v_2, \ldots, v_n</m>.
      </p>
      <p>
        This takes a bit of getting used to, and the hardest part is the choice
        of signs. We choose a positive sign if the vectors
        <m>v_1, v_2, \ldots, v_n</m> have the same orientation as the standard
        basis.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection>
    <title>Sage and the Determinant</title>
    <p>Sage has a built-in command for the determinant of a square matrix. It is
      just what you expect: <c>A.determinant()</c>.
    </p>
    <sage>
      <input>
        A = matrix(QQ, 3,3, [4,3,5, 2,-1,0, -5,2,10])
        A
      </input>
      <output>
        [ 4  3  5]
        [ 2 -1  0]
        [-5  2 10]
      </output>
    </sage>
    <p>To be sure that this works properly, we can do it the old way, too:</p>
    <sage>
      <input>
        P, L, U = A.LU(pivot="nonzero")
        print(P)
        print(L)
        print(U)
      </input>
      <output>
        [1 0 0]
        [0 1 0]
        [0 0 1]
        [     1      0      0]
        [   1/2      1      0]
        [  -5/4 -23/10      1]
        [   4    3    5]
        [   0 -5/2 -5/2]
        [   0    0 21/2]
      </output>
    </sage>
    <p>
      Clearly, there are no row swaps used, so it is easy to see that
      <m>\det(A) = 4*(-5/2)*(21/2) = -105</m>.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Exercises</title>

  </subsection>
</section>
