<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the workbook                        -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--    Math 2500: Linear Algebra                             -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2014  Theron J. Hitchman                   -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<section xml:id="soln-gf">
  <title>Going Further with Solving Systems</title>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Assignment</title>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Go back through the exercises in the first four sections of this chapter.
        Complete any items you
        did not complete the first time through. Prepare any that we have not
        discussed in class so that you will be ready to present them.
      </li>
    </ul>

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Discussion</title>


    <p>Now we take a short break to revisit and consolidate the learning you
      have done so far. Revisit the reading and the exercises you have done in
      the first four sections of Chapter Three: Vector Space and Subspaces. The
      important feature of this work should be
      learning to think about your own thinking. This sort of <term>meta-cognition</term>
      characterizes expert learners. Eventually, you want to be able to monitor
      your work at all times and recognize when you understand deeply and when
      you do not. This will allow you to self-correct.
    </p>
    <p>To help you get started with meta-cognition, I listed learning goals in
      each section. To go further, you need to explicitly go through the process
      of reviewing what you can do and what you cannot. Here are some prompts to
      help you get started with this process.
      <ul>
        <li>
          Review the learning goals from each section. Can you do the things
          described? Can you do them sometimes, or have you mastered them so you
          can do them consistently?
        </li>
        <li>
          Look through all of the tasks and go deeper into them. Can you
          connect each exercise to one of our pictures? Try to build a mental
          model of how the exercise and its solution work.
        </li>
        <li>
          If your first solution to an exercise involve a <q>guess-and-check</q>
          approach, can you now complete the exercise in a <em>purposeful</em>
          and systematic manner?
        </li>
        <li>
          Make a list of concepts or exercises that are not clear to you. Phrase
          each item in your list as a question, and make each question as
          specific as possible. Talk with fellow students or your
          instructor until you can answer your own questions.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

</section>
