<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the workbook                        -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--    Math 2500: Linear Algebra                             -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2014  Theron J. Hitchman                   -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<section xml:id="two-pictures">
  <title>Two Geometric Models</title>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Assignment</title>

    <ul>
      <li>
        Read section 2.1 of <em>Strang</em> (pages 31-40).
      </li>
      <li>
        Read the following and complete the exercises below
      </li>
    </ul>

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Learning Goals</title>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Discussion</title>

    <p>
      Now we have a little experience with vectors and related things, it is
      time to be aware of what we have done so we can use it as a foundation for
      future work. So far, we have talked about two geometric interpretations
      for a system of linear equations, the <term>row picture</term> and the
      <term>column picture</term>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Does the following picture make sense to you?
    </p>

    <p>
      A deep understanding of linear algebra will involve a level of comfort with
      each of these three views of the subject in the diagram, and also the ability
      to pass back and forth between them.
    </p>

    <subsubsection>
      <title>The Transformational View</title>

      <p>
        We have seen that matrices can be made to "act upon" vectors by a kind of
        multiplication. In particular, if <m>A</m> is an <m>m\times n</m> matrix,
        then <m>A</m> can be multiplied (on the left) with a column vector of size
        <m>n</m>, and the result is a column vector of size <m>m</m>.
      </p>
      <p>
        This makes <m>A</m> into a kind of <term>function</term>. (We will use
        the synonyms <term>mapping</term> or <term>transformation</term>, too.)
        For every vector <m>v</m> of size <m>n</m>, the matrix <m>A</m> allows
        us to compute a new vector <m>T_A(v) = Av</m> of size <m>m</m>. This is
        the basic example of what we will eventually call a <term>linear
        transformation</term>.<md>
        <mrow>\mathbb{R}^m &amp; \xrightarrow[]{T_A} \mathbb{R}^n</mrow>
        <mrow>v &amp; \xmapsto[]{\phantom{T_A}} Av.</mrow></md>
        One of our long term goals is to find a way to think about the geometry
        of linear algebra from this viewpoint, too.
      </p>

    </subsubsection>


  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Sage and xxx</title>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        translate a system to a lin comb
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        translate a lin comb into a system
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        Consider the matrix equation<me>
        \begin{pmatrix}1 &amp; 2 &amp; 4 \\ 2 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 \end{pmatrix}
          \begin{pmatrix} x \\ y \\ z \end{pmatrix} = \begin{pmatrix} -1 \\ 3
          \end{pmatrix}.
        </me>
        <ol>
          <li>
            Draw a diagram representing the row picture of this matrix equation.
          </li>
          <li>
            Draw a diagram representing the column picture of this matrix equation.
          </li>
        </ol>
      </statement>
    </exercise>



    <exercise>
      <statement>
        Find an example of a system of linear equations so that the
        corresponding column picture is about lin combs of 4 2-vecs = 0
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        Find a lin comb equation so that the corresponding system of linear eqns
        means intersect 3 lines in the plane.
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        Find an example of a vector <m>b</m> so that the equation<me>
          \begin{pmatrix} -1 &amp; 2 \\ 5 &amp; -9 \end{pmatrix} v = b
        </me>
        has no solution <m>v</m>, or explain why it is impossible to find
        such an example.
      </statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise>
      <statement>
        In each of the below, find an example of a matrix <m>B</m> which has the
        described effect.
        <ol>
          <li>
            <m>
              B\begin{pmatrix} x \\ y \end{pmatrix} = \begin{pmatrix}y \\ x \end{pmatrix}
            </m>
          </li>
          <li>
            Rotates vectors through <m>45^{\circ}</m> counter-clockwise.
          </li>
          <li>
            Reflects vectors across the <m>y</m>axis.
          </li>
          <li>
            <m>
              B\begin{pmatrix} x \\ y \end{pmatrix} =
              \begin{pmatrix} x+y \\ y \end{pmatrix}.
            </m>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </statement>
    </exercise>



  </subsection>



</section>
