<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the workbook                        -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!--    Math 2500: Linear Algebra                             -->
<!--                                                          -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2014  Theron J. Hitchman                   -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.             -->

<section xml:id="vector-spaces">
  <title>Subspaces of <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m></title>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Assignment</title>
    <ul>
      <li>Read Chapter 3 section 1 of <em>Strang</em>.</li>
      <li>Read the following and complete the exercises below.</li>
    </ul>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Learning Goals</title>
    <p>Before class, a student should be able to:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Identify the column space of a matrix.</li>
      <li>Decide if a set in <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> is a subspace or not.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Some time after class, a student should be able to:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Use the notion of column space to decide if a given linear system has a
        solution or not.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Discussion: Vector Spaces and Subspaces</title>
    <p>
      The key concepts in this section are those of a <term>vector space</term>
      and of a <term>subspace</term>. The basic idea is that a vector space is
      a kind of place where the basic operations involved in a linear
      combination make sense. There is a set of rules for being a vector space,
      but they are all aimed at the fact that there are two operations
      (addition and scalar multiplication) and we can form linear combinations
      with them that make sense.
    </p>
    <p>
      The biggest thing is that we possibly enlarge the kinds of things we
      call <q>vectors.</q> To a professional mathematician, a vector is
      anything that is an element of some vector space under consideration.
      My favorites are things like this:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        The set <m>M_{2,2}</m> of <m>2\times 2</m> matrices is a vector space.
        But now the things we call vectors are actually matrices.
      </li>
      <li>
        The set <m>\mathcal{C}(\mathbb{R})</m> of continuous functions with
        domain and range both equal to the set of real numbers is a vector
        space. But now the things we call vectors are actually functions.
      </li>
      <li>
        The set <m>\ell(\mathbb{R})</m> of sequences
        <m>(x_1, x_2, x_3, x_4, \ldots)</m> of real numbers is a vector space.
        But now the things we call vectors are actually whole infinite sequences.
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      In more advanced mathematics, vector spaces are extremely important. They
      show up everywhere. But for us, we will mostly stick to the family of vector
      spaces <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>. It will be much more important for us to understand
      subspaces.
    </p>
    <p>
      The idea of a subspace is some subset, some part, of a vector space which
      is a vector space in its own right. The prototype is the <m>xy</m>-plane
      inside of <m>\mathbb{R}^3</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      For now, the most important subspaces we see will be derived from
      individual matrices. Our first example is the column space of a matrix
      <m>A</m>. If <m>A</m> is an <m>m\times n</m> matrix, then the column
      space <m>\mathrm{col}(A)</m> of <m>A</m> is the collection of
      <m>n</m>-vectors which can be expressed as linear combinations of the
      columns of <m>A</m>. This is our first exposure to the idea of a
      <term>span</term>. The column space of <m>A</m> is the subspace of
      <m>\mathbb{R}</m> spanned by the columns of <m>A</m>.
    </p>



  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>SageMath and subspaces</title>

    <p>SageMath allows you to construct different kinds of vector spaces. The most
      important is the standard vector space <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>.
    </p>
    <sage>
      <input>
        V = VectorSpace(QQ, 3)
        V
      </input>
      <output>Vector space of dimension 3 over Rational Field</output>
    </sage>
    <p>
      This is like the <c>MatrixSpace</c> construction we have seen before.
      <c>V</c> is now the collection of all vectors of size <m>3</m> with
      rational numbers as entries.
    </p>
    <p>
      More important for us is the fact that SageMath knows how to find the subspaces
      associated to matrices.
    </p>
    <sage>
      <input>
        A = matrix(QQ, 2,3, [4,5,3,0,1,1])
        A
      </input>
      <output>
        [4 5 3]
        [0 1 1]
      </output>
    </sage>
    <sage>
      <input>
        A.column_space()
      </input>
      <output>
        Vector space of degree 2 and dimension 2 over Rational Field
        Basis matrix:
        [1 0]
        [0 1]
      </output>
    </sage>
    <p>
      Note that SageMath gives information in terms of a basis. We will talk about
      this concept soon.
    </p>
    <sage>
      <input>
        B = matrix(QQ, 3,3 , [1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9])
        B
      </input>
      <output>
        [1 2 3]
        [4 5 6]
        [7 8 9]
      </output>
    </sage>
    <sage>
      <input>B.column_space()</input>
      <output>
        Vector space of degree 3 and dimension 2 over Rational Field
        Basis matrix:
        [ 1  0 -1]
        [ 0  1  2]
      </output>
    </sage>
    <p>
      This last bit here is interesting.
      Our original matrix has size <m>2\times 3</m>, so the columns are <m>3</m>-vectors.
      But this basis is displayed as a matrix where the columns are size <m>2</m>.
      What is going on?
    </p>
    <p>
      SageMath prefers to display vectors as rows! This is a big interal preference.
      We just have to get over it. Well, we have to <em>remember it</em> and get over it.
      To access the basis vectors and display them as columns,
      we will use the following:
    </p>
    <sage>
      <input>
        B.column_space().basis()[0].column() # first basis vector
      </input>
      <output>
        [ 1]
        [ 0]
        [-1]
      </output>
    </sage>
    <sage>
      <input>
        B.column_space().basis()[1].column() # second basis vector
      </input>
      <output>
        [0]
        [1]
        [2]
      </output>
    </sage>

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <task>
      <statement>
        Find an example of a vector which is not in the column space of the
        matrix <me>
        A = \begin{pmatrix} 2 &amp; 1  \\ 1 &amp; 1 \end{pmatrix},
        </me> or explain why that is not possible.
      </statement>
    </task>

    <task>
      <statement>
        Find an example of a vector which is not in the column space of the
        matrix <me>
        B = \begin{pmatrix} 3 &amp; 2 \\ 6 &amp; 4 \end{pmatrix},
        </me> or explain why it is not possible.
      </statement>
    </task>

    <task>
      <statement>
        Let <m>\mathcal{P}</m> be the set of polynomials of degree 3 or less.
        Explain why <m>\mathcal{P}</m> is a vector space, or explain why it is not.
      </statement>
    </task>

    <task>
      <statement>
        Consider the vector space <m>\mathbb{R}^2</m>. Explain why the following
        are not subspaces:
        <ul>
          <li>The unit circle.</li>
          <li>The line <m>x+y = 4</m>.</li>
          <li>The union of lines <m>2x+3y = 0</m> and <m>x-y=0</m>.</li>
          <li>The first quadrant where <m>x\geq 0</m> and <m>y\geq 0</m>.</li>
        </ul>
      </statement>
    </task>

    <task>
      <statement>
        Let <m>W</m> be the set of functions <m>f</m> in
        <m>\mathcal{C}(\mathbb{R})</m> which satisfy the differential equation
        <m>f''(x) = 0</m>. Decide if <m>W</m> is a subspace of
        <m>\mathcal{C}(\mathbb{R})</m>, and explain your thinking.
      </statement>
    </task>

    <task>
      <statement>
        Design a <m>2\times 3</m> matrix whose column space does not contain the
        vector <m>\begin{pmatrix} 4 \\ 4 \end{pmatrix}</m>, or explain why this is
        not possible.
      </statement>
    </task>


  </subsection>

</section>
