<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Course Page for UNI Math 2500</description>
    <link>http://theronhitchman.github.io/linear-algebra/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://theronhitchman.github.io/linear-algebra/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Our First Meeting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Success! I mean that TWO ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We had a good first day, and we got to preview some important ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I found my notebook! That is, one of my other students reminded me that
I took it to the back of the classroom in my 1pm class. HaHA! Crisis Averted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had one spectacular failure today. I mispronounced Mr Covid’s name over and over
again. I should have said “Covid,” but instead I kept saying “Corvid.” What’s weird
is that &lt;em&gt;corvid&lt;/em&gt; is a name for a family of related bird species including crows,
ravens, and jays. They are known to be intelligent birds who can solve problems.
Maybe Mr &lt;strike&gt;Corvid&lt;/strike&gt;Covid can forgive me. (embarrassed smiley face here)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since there were more of you than I expected, I ran out of syllabi. If you did
not get a paper copy today, please fetch it from the link in the navigation bar
at the top of this web page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-wednesday&quot;&gt;For Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please do the assignment as listed in the workbook section 1.1. This has several
parts, including&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reading from Strang,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reading from the workbook itself,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;watching a youTube video, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trying out some tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can already start reading while I get to work on editing the problems. None
of the text will change, just the selection of exercises. I’ll share a bit more
about how to complete this later tonight. In particular, I will give you some
ideas about how to read effectively. I am off to write that down in a minute,
I only just thought to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advance-warning&quot;&gt;Advance Warning:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, we will hold class in WRT 110, a computer lab across the hall from our
regular room. More details on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 15:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://theronhitchman.github.io/linear-algebra/2016/08/22/First-Day.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://theronhitchman.github.io/linear-algebra/2016/08/22/First-Day.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Linear Algebra</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This course blog will serve a dual purpose. First, it will give us all a
common record of what transpires in class. Second, it will be a way for me to
make announcements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you happen to miss a day, you can keep up by following along here. And if
you find you can’t recall what happened on a particular day, or who had which
great idea, this is the place to look.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2016 17:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://theronhitchman.github.io/linear-algebra/2016/08/20/welcome.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://theronhitchman.github.io/linear-algebra/2016/08/20/welcome.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
